So I'm aware that there's a big risk that you are getting fed up of leaderboards, because we've done
여러분이 순위표에 질릴 위험이 있다는 걸 압니다 순위표에
a lot of talking about leaderboards, and perhaps you are becoming fatigued to looking at benchmarks
대해 많은 얘기를 나눴는데 벤치마크와 순위표만 보는 데 지쳤을 수도 있어요
You've bookmarked them all.
다 즐겨찾기 해놨잖아요
You're thinking, okay, I get it.
Get it, get it, get.라고 생각하죠
There are lots of great resources when it comes to choosing an LMS.
LMS를 선택할 때 훌륭한 리소스가 많아요
I will look through your leaderboards and I will do it then.
리더보드를 보고 나서 그렇게 할게요
But enough.
하지만 그만하죠
Enough with the leaderboards.
순위표는 그만 봐요
But wait, there is one more.
잠깐만요, 하나 더 있어요
And it's a really fun one.
정말 재미있어요
And it's one you're going to love.
여러분도 좋아하실 거예요
So you're not going to mind this final leaderboard for us to look at.
그러니 순위표는 신경 쓰지 않아도 되겠죠
And it is in fact not a normal leaderboard.
사실 평범한 순위표는 아니에요
It is an arena and it's called the LMS Chatbot Arena.
LMS 챗봇 아레나라는 아레나예요
And you may have come across this already because it's so popular and fun and lots of people talk about
이미 들어봤을 거예요 아주 인기 있고 재미있고 많은 사람이 얘기하니까요
it.
이미 알고 계신다면 조금만 더 기다려 주세요 함께 사용해 보면서 재밌게 해 볼
some fun.
테니까요
So the idea is that the LMS chatbot arena, which is incredibly popular, is a place where models are
LMS 챗봇 아레나는 아주 인기가 많은데 채팅 능력을 평가하는
assessed by humans and they're assessed for their chat abilities.
참가자들이 모델을 평가하는 곳이죠
It is, as they say, a crowdsourced open platform.
크라우드소싱한 오픈 플랫폼이라고 하죠
They've collected over a million human votes, ranking llms and to display results in as as I say,
100만 개가 넘는 인권 투표를 모아 llms의 순위를 매기고 결과를 표시합니다 체스 선수들에게
in what's called an Elo rating type that will be familiar to chess players.
익숙한 Elo 평가 방식이죠
It's a way of assessing an overall kind of leaderboard based on the outcomes of head to head battles.
헤드 라이딩의 결과에 따라 전체 순위표를 평가하는 방식이에요
And you can see here some of the results.
여기 결과를 좀 보세요
And we will now take a look at what we see in first place is a variant of GPT four called ChatGPT 4.0
지금부터 살펴볼 것은 1위에 오른 GPT 4의 변종입니다 챗GPT 4라고 하죠 최근에 나온 0개요
As of recording this video, it came out in early August 2024, and that previously GPT four was a little
이 영상은 2024년 8월 초에 공개됐는데 이전 GPT 4는 순위표에서 조금 더 아래였어요
bit further down on this list.
비트 코어링
But with this latest trained, fine tuned model, uh ChatGPT four has taken the top position in the
하지만 최신식 정교하게 훈련된 모델 챗GPT 4가 Elo 1을 기록하며 이 경기장의
arena with an Elo of 1.316.
선두를 차지했죠 316번요
Uh.
네
A useful thing here is that the knowledge cut off is quoted over on the right.
여기서 유용한 건 지식이 차단된 부분이 오른쪽에 인용됐다는 거죠
And so it's a if you want one place to go to see all the knowledge cut offs.
모든 지식을 단절된 곳을 한 군데서 보고 싶다면요
Actually, the, uh, open the LMS chatbot arena is a good place to go, so that's worth knowing.
LMS 챗봇 아레나도 좋은 곳이니까 알아두면 좋죠
I don't think it's it's intended to be its primary reason, but it's a useful tidbit.
그게 주요한 이유가 될 의도는 아니었을 거예요 하지만 유용한 정보죠
Um, you'll see that Gemini 1.5 Pro actually is is doing really well in this human evaluated assessment.
제미니 1호가 보일 거예요 5프로 이즈는 인체 평가에서 아주 잘하고 있어요
Um, grok two, which is the latest model from X, uh, formerly known as Twitter is in strong place
그록 2는 트위터였던 엑스 사의 최신 모델로 현재 강세를 보이고
here.
있죠
Uh, grok one had not done so well.
그록 1은 잘하지 못했어요
Grok two is really doing very well.
그록 2는 아주 잘하고 있어요
Um, and it's beating the earlier GPT four zero from, from May.
5월 GPT 40 기록을 앞섰어요
Um, and uh, it's, uh, yeah.
네, 맞아요
Uh, and you can see there's not much in that ELO difference, but at this point there is fairly significant
ELO에서는 차이가 별로 안 나지만 현재 1위인 클로드
difference from the the leader Claude 3.5 Sonet, which at one point was was the front runner by by
3과는 상당히 큰 차이가 있어요 5 소넷은 한때 선두주자였어요
I think by quite a way, if I remember right when it came out has now come down to, uh, I guess equal,
제 기억으로는 출시 당시만 해도요 지금은 거의 6위까지 올라왔고요
Um, uh, right down here in, in, uh, Elo of 1270 compared to 1316 for the top, uh, GPT chat,
여기 아래는 1270이고 위쪽은 1316이에요 GPT 채팅방은 1316이고
GPT four zero, um, then Gemini 1.5 flash, which of course is a somewhat smaller model.
그다음은 제미니 1호죠 5 플래시요 물론 좀 더 작은 모델이죠
And here comes llama 3.1 405 billion at 1266.
라마 3이 나오네요 1266에 1억 4,500억 달러요
Uh, so, uh, yeah, very interesting to see this lineup.
이 라인업을 보는 게 아주 흥미로워요
You can keep going to find your favorite models.
좋아하는 모델을 계속 찾을 수 있어요
Claude three opus is way down here.
클로드 3백작은 이 아래에 있어요
Uh, and, uh, yeah, this is a great place to get a sense of how humans consider the experience of
그리고 여긴 사용법이 정립된 다양한 챗봇과 채팅하는 경험을 인간이 어떻게 생각하는지
chatting with different, uh, instruction tuned uh, chatbots.
알 수 있는 좋은 곳이에요 Get it
Uh, you'll see that, uh, um, command r that we were looking at before.
아까 봤던 명령 r이 보일 거예요
Uh, I just saw command R that features somewhere here.
명령어 R이 여기 어디 있는 걸 봤어요
Uh, you will have to find that yourself.
그건 스스로 찾아야 해요
I've now lost it.
이제 못 하겠어요
There it is.
저기 있네요
Command R plus found it.
커맨드 R 플러스예요
Uh, there it is at 1213.
12시 13분이에요
Uh, it's one of the ones we looked at all the way back at the start in week one.
첫째 주에 시작할 때부터 계속 살펴본 부분이에요
So this is the famous LM, uh, LMS chatbot arena, and you can vote by clicking on this link, and
여기는 그 유명한 LMS 챗봇 아레나입니다 이 링크를 클릭하면 투표할 수 있어요 그럼
it will bring up this voting screen.
이 투표 화면이 나오죠
And here's how it works.
이렇게 하는 거예요
You get presented with two models model A and model B.
모델 A와 B가 두 가지씩 준비돼 있어요. Get it.
You don't know which one is which and you have to chat with them both.
누가 누군지 모르고 둘 다와 대화를 해야 해요
And so let's do one of our favorite little chat things.
우리가 좋아하는 간단한 대화를 해보죠
Uh, please tell me a light hearted light hearted joke suitable for a room full of data scientists.
가벼운 농담 하나 해 주세요 데이터 과학자들이 가득한 방에 어울리는 거로요
So this question will be asked to both models together and we will see how they answer.
두 모델이 동시에 이 질문을 받고 어떻게 대답하는지 보죠
So the model A why do the data scientists break up with a computer?
모델 A는 왜 과학자들이 컴퓨터와 분리하는 걸까요?
Because it had too many commitment issues with its null values.
아무 가치도 없는 가치 때문에 헌신에 문제가 많았거든요
Okay, they did sciency, but not funny, I don't think.
과학적이긴 했지만 재미는 없었어요
Maybe you found it funny.
재미있었나 보죠
And model B, please tell me a joke.
모델 B, 농담 하나 해 주세요
Here is a light hearted joke.
가벼운 농담이 있어요
Why does scientists go to the library?
과학자들은 왜 라이브러리에 가죠?
Because they heard it had a lot of volumes.
양이 많다고 들었거든요
Oh, yeah, that's pretty good, right?
네, 꽤 괜찮죠?
That's that's different plays on the dual meaning word volumes.
그건 이중적 의미의 볼륨을 사용하는 거예요
It gives a little explanation.
설명이 나오죠
The joke is simple.
농담은 간단해요
It's kind of pun that data scientists tend to appreciate as it combines technical expertise with a bit
데이터 과학자들이 좋아하는 말장난이죠 기술적 전문성과 약간의 말장난이 합쳐진
of wordplay.
거니까요 비트
I think that's solid.
튼튼한 것 같아요
That's solid.
탄탄하네요
Uh, I think B is better, is what I want to go with.
B가 더 나은 것 같아요
Hopefully you agree with me.
동의하시길 바라요
Uh, if not, you need to go into the arena and do, uh, do a ask a similar question and make your
그게 아니라면 경기장에 들어가서 비슷한 질문을 하고 투표하세요
own vote, but I'm going to vote on your behalf on all of our behalves by pressing the B is better button,
하지만 제가 여러분을 대신해 투표하겠습니다 B가 더 낫다 버튼을 누르면
and it will then reveal the models.
모델이 공개될 거예요
Let's see.
어디 보죠
Uh, interestingly, the we picked Claude three haiku and we picked that against grok two.
흥미롭게도 클로드 3 하이쿠와 그록 2를 대조했어요
Uh, if I remember right, grok two was quite significantly higher than Claude three haiku.
제 기억이 맞는다면 그록 2가 클로드 3 하이쿠보다 훨씬 높았어요
So we have slightly fractionally shifted that balance through our vote.
투표를 통해 균형이 약간 흔들린 거죠
So I hope you enjoyed that.
즐겁게 보셨길 바라요
Of course, that was somewhat unscientific, but the idea is it's meant to be a human decision based
물론 비과학적인 방법이긴 하지만 상호 작용에 근거해 인간이 결정해야
on your interaction.
한다는 게 핵심이죠
And the ask for you now is go and do this.
지금 당신에게 필요한 건 가서 이걸 하는 거예요
It's an important way to add back to the community.
지역 사회에 다시 기여하는 중요한 방법이죠
It is data that will be used.
사용될 데이터는 데이터죠
Uh, plus it's a it's a lot of fun.
게다가 정말 재미있어요
Uh, and it gives you a bit of sense of the capabilities and scope of the different models and some
다양한 모델의 기능과 스코프를 알게 되고 직접 체험해 보는 경험을
hands on experience whilst contributing back to the data science community.
통해 데이터 과학계에 비트를 더할 수 있죠
So enjoy spending some time on the chatbot arena, and I will see you next time to talk about commercial
챗봇 아레나에서 즐거운 시간 보내시고 다음 시간에는 상업적 용도에 대해 얘기
uses.
나누죠